{"tossups": [{"question": "This man was the chief lawyer to Attorney General John Mitchell when he was chosen to replace the retiring John Marshall Harlan II. While clerking for Robert Jackson, this man wrote that he thought\u201c<em>Plessy v. Ferguson</em> was right.\u201d This man, the first member of the Supreme Court since 1954 to die in office, voted on cases like<em> Lawrence v. Texas</em> with Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas in a conservative bloc. Warren Burger was succeeded as Chief Justice by, for the point, what judge who was himself succeeded as Chief Justice by John Roberts in 2005?", "answer": "William<b> Rehnquist</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1910, White Rock Creek was dammed to create a reservoir for this city. A park in this city contains a concrete pergola named for its founder John Neely Bryan. The Leonhardt Lagoon and Hall of State are located in its Fair Park area. A \u201csixth floor museum\u201d in this city commemorates an event in which a man hiding in a Book Depository fired on a motorcade passing through this city\u2019s Dealey Plaza. For the point, name this city where Lee Harvey Oswald assassinated John F. Kennedy in North Texas.", "answer": "<b> Dallas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A controversial statue of this man by Horatio Greenough shows him robed and seated like Zeus. Another work shows this man resting against the<em> fasces</em> with a plow behind him; that work is located in the Virginia State Capitol. James Monroe holds a flag in a painting by Emmanuel Leutze that features this man leading troops towards Trenton in a boat across an icy river. For the point, name this man who appears, as depicted by Gilbert Stuart, on the American one-dollar bill.", "answer": "George<b> Washington</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One cause of this event was a letter sent by Dr. Charles Cooper to a participant\u2019s father-in-law that disparaged the other participant\u2019s campaign for governor. It is believed that the victim of this event\u201cdeloped,\u201d as he had recommended his son do in a similar situation three years earlier at the same place, Weehawken Heights in New Jersey. For the point, name this 1804 incident in which a sitting Vice President killed a former Secretary of the Treasury.", "answer": "the<b> duel</b> between Alexander<b> Hamilton</b> and Aaron<b> Burr</b> (accept names in either order, and any description that includes all three aspects; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Captain Henry Ross designed a symbol for members of this profession. Peter Lalor led these workers, who had earlier been enticed by Thomas Hiscock to travel to Buninyong. The Ballarat Reform League represented these workers, who mobilized for combat on Bakery Hill and hoisted the Eureka flag during a stockade rebellion. Melbourne turned into a major boom town thanks to these workers, who scrambled to reach the Fish River. For the point, name this profession which boomed during the Victorian Gold Rush.", "answer": "Australian gold<b> miners</b> (prompt on Australians)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader punished his bodyguards after a picture of him falling down from a podium was widely mocked on the internet in early 2015. In 2008, this leader\u2019s British knighthood was revoked after he fraudulently won against the opposing Movement for Democratic Change Party led by Morgan Tsvangarai [chon-gee-rye]. This leader transitioned into using the US dollar after his country\u2019s own currency inflated by 79 billion percent in November 2008. For the point, name this leader of the ZANU-PF Party and President of Zimbabwe.", "answer": "Robert<b> Mugabe</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "D. Louis Abood\u2019s refusal to join one of these organizations led to a lawsuit against the Detroit Board of Education. The Supreme Court ruled in<em> Harris v. Quinn</em> that these organizations are not allowed to collect fees from non-members, overturning a provision of the Taft-Hartley Act, even though non-members may still benefit from collective bargaining done by these organizations. For the point, name these groups that promote better working conditions and higher wages by organizing workers.", "answer": "labor<b> union</b>s (or trade<b> union</b>s, etc.; accept educational<b> union</b>s; accept descriptions of medical <b>union</b>s after \u201cHarris\u201d is read) (10) In 2016, an insurance agent claiming to be a spokesperson for this team managed to meet with Sudanese president Omar Al-Bashir. Prior to a 11-1 defeat to their biggest rivals, players from this team were allegedly intimidated by police sympathetic to Francisco Franco. This team\u2019s status as a nationalist symbol is reflected by its slogan \u201cMes que un club.\u201d For the point, name this Spanish football team whose\u201cEl Clasico\u201d rivalry with Real Madrid is seen as a metaphor for the struggle for Catalonian independence. ANSWER: FC<b> Barcelona</b> (or<b> Barca</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This country lost most of its territory in the Treaty of Trianon, but it regained some in the Vienna Awards. This country twice refused the rule of Charles IV, its last king, and instead was led through World War II by Admiral Mikl\u00b4os Horthy. A relaxed form of communism called Goulash communism developed in, for the point, what country whose 1956 revolution was led by Imre Nagy [nazh] but crushed by Soviet tanks rolling through Budapest?", "answer": "<b> Hungary</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This group of people lost the Battle of Telamon despite the participation of Gaesatae mercenaries. One leader of these people sieged Clusium, proceeded to win the Battle of the Allia, and then said \u201cwoe to the defeated!\u201d while measuring a tribute payment. Another leader of these people won the Battle of Gergovia but was defeated in the siege of Alesia by Julius Caesar. Brennus and Vercingetorix were part of, for the point, what group of barbarians who lived primarily in modern-day France?", "answer": "<b> Gaul</b>s (prompt on Celts)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The Urabi Revolt was an attempt to liberate this country from European interests. This country was known as a khedivate after it was taken over by an Albanian ruler named Muhammad Ali. After the fall of the Ayyubids, soldier slaves known as Mamluks established a sultanate in this country that ruled until its 1517 defeat by the Ottoman Empire. The Free Officers Movement triggered a republican revolution in, for the point, what north African country where Gamal Abdel Nasser ruled from Cairo?", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This character drowns his brother in a vat of wine after claiming that he is \u201cdetermined to prove a villain.\u201d This character hires James Tyrell to murder his nephews after working with Buckingham to spread rumors of their legitimacy. This king states that \u201cnow is the winter of our discontent made glorious by this sun of York\u201d at the beginning of a play named for him. For the point, name this hunchbacked king who titles a Shakespeare history play and died at the Battle of Bosworth Field.", "answer": "<b> Richard III</b> (prompt on Richard; prompt on Duke of Gloucester)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "Warren Christopher negotiated the end of this event by unfreezing nearly $8 billion in assets. Eight Americans died when a helicopter and plane collided during Operation Eagle Claw, a failed attempt to end this event. This event\u2019s end was timed to coincide with the inauguration ceremonies for Ronald Reagan, whose victory over Jimmy Carter was possibly clinched by Carter\u2019s failure to end this event. For the point, name this crisis in which 52 Americans were captured and held for 444 days in Tehran.", "answer": "<b> Iran</b>ian<b> hostage</b> crisis (accept descriptive answers that describe American<b> hostage</b>s being captured, held, and/or released in<b> Iran</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This colony\u2019s independence movement was sparked by the S\u00b4etif Massacre, and its independence war started on Red All Saints\u2019 Day. Both pro- and anti-independence figures in this colony\u2019s European ruler were targeted by bombings in the Caf\u00b4e Wars. The flight of the<em> pied-noirs</em> [peed-nwar], Europeans residing in this colony, was accelerated by the Oran Massacre, which began on the day that its independence was established through the 1962 Evian Accords. The FLN fought for independence in, for the point, what French colony in North Africa?", "answer": "French<b> Algeria</b> (prompt on (French) North Africa before said)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s Opus 40 no. 1, a work in A major, was played daily over the radio by one country in World War II and is nicknamed \u201cMilitary.\u201d This man borrowed a form invented by Irish pianist John Field for many of his pieces, and commemorated his native land\u2019s November Uprising with the<em> Revolutionary\u00b4Etude</em>. For the point, name this Polish-born Romantic pianist, known for composing many nocturnes, mazurkas, and polonaises.", "answer": "Fr\u00b4ed\u00b4eric Fran\u00b8cois<b> Chopin</b> (or Fryderyk Franciszek<b> Chopin</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "England garrisoned troops in three of this country\u2019s \u201cCautionary Towns,\u201d including Brielle [breel]. Siege warfare was revolutionised by a general from this country, the stadtholder Maurice of Nassau. This country gained its independence from Spain in the Eighty Years\u2019 War and was succeeded by the Batavian Republic. The House of Orange ruled, for the point, what European country that was later known as Holland and is currently governed from Amsterdam?", "answer": "Republic of the Seven United<b> Netherlands</b> (or the<b> Netherlands</b>; accept<b> Dutch</b> Republic; accept Republic of the Seven<b> United Provinces</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A member of this family wrote the book<em> Countercoup</em> about his role in the 1953 Iranian coup. Two members of this family journeyed down the \u201cRiver of Doubt\u201d in South America in the 1910\u2019s. A member of this family proclaimed \u201cwe stand at Armageddon and we battle for the Lord\u201d when accepting the nomination of the Progressive, or Bull Moose, Party. That member of this family promised the \u201cSquare Deal\u201d for his presidency and gave the foreign policy advice of \u201cspeak softly and carry a big stick.\u201d For the point, name this American family that includes a President nicknamed \u201cTeddy.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Roosevelt</b> (accept Kermit and/or Theodore \u201cTeddy\u201d<b> Roosevelt</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this empire, nobles were assigned ranks of \u201czat\u201d and \u201csawar,\u201d based on the military forces they maintained, within the mansabdari system. One of this empire\u2019s rulers established the Din-i Ilahi religion and founded the Ibadat Khana, or House of Worship, as a place for religious dialogue. Another ruler of this empire was married to Mumtaz and built her an elaborate mausoleum. Babur founded this empire, which reached its height under Akbar the Great. For the point, name this Muslim empire that constructed the Taj Mahal.", "answer": "<b> Mughal</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1962, Neil Bartlett bonded one of these things with platinum hexafluoride. For discovering some of these things, Lord Rayleigh and William Ramsay won the 1904 Nobel Prizes in Physics and Chemistry. Archaeologists working with specimens older than 100,000 years study the decay of potassium into one of these elements in a common form of radioactive dating. For the point, name this group of elements whose full valence shells make them highly unreactive, a group that includes krypton, argon, and neon.", "answer": "<b> noble gas</b>es (or<b> inert gas</b>es; accept<b> Group 18</b> of the periodic table; prompt on gas before\u201cfull valence shells\u201d is read; prompt on element before said)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "In the 17th century, this city suffered Salt and Copper Riots over taxes and currency debasement. A ruler of this city won the Battle of Kulikovo to free his people from the Tatars. Women helped build defenses to prevent Operation Typhoon, a German invasion of this city, while a French offensive ended with the burning of this city after the Battle of Borodino. In 1812, a retreating Napoleon ordered the demolition of the Kremlin in, for the point, what capital of Russia?", "answer": "<b> Moscow</b> or<b> Moskva</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "After Black Friday, William \u201cTonnage\u201d Tunner revitalized the effort to supply this city, the home of Tempelhof Airport. This city\u2019s \u201cghost stations,\u201d or abandoned train stops, appeared after Erich Honecker built a structure with a \u201cdeath strip\u201d on one side. Gail Halvorsen dropped chocolate on this city during a 1948-49 airlift that skirted a Soviet blockade. For the point, name this European city that was divided into West and East halves by a wall that fell in 1989.", "answer": "<b> Berlin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this 1781 defeat for Charles Cornwallis that led to the end of the Revolutionary War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Yorktown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This song was quoted at the end of Al Gore\u2019s Presidential concession speech in 2000. In its modern form, this song replaces the word \u201chalcyon\u201d from the first line of Katharine Lee Bates\u2019 original poem with the word \u201cspacious,\u201d and describes not an \u201cenameled plain,\u201d but a \u201cfruited plain.\u201d Bates\u2019 trip to Pikes Peak inspired this song, whose first stanza ends with the call to \u201ccrown thy good with brotherhood/From sea to shining sea.\u201d For the point, name this patriotic song that describes the \u201cspacious skies\u201d and \u201camber waves of grain\u201d of the United States.", "answer": "<b> America the Beautiful</b> (do not accept or prompt on America alone) Page 6", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "In this country, members of the rock band Plastic People of the Universe were arrested for disturbing the peace, inspiring the writing of Charter 77. A 2,000-word manifesto written by Ludvik Vaculik supported a progressive movement that began in this country in January 1968 with the rise of Alexander Dub\u02d8cek [doob-check], who promoted \u201csocialism with a human face\u201d against the wishes of the Soviets. For the point, name this European country that underwent the 1968 Prague Spring and dissolved into two countries in 1993.", "answer": "<b> Czechoslovakia</b> (do not accept Czech Republic or Slovakia)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A plaster cast of this figure by Salvador Dali includes drawers and pom-poms. A Neolithic figurine found in Austria was known as this goddess of Willendorf. A painting of this goddess shows two winged figures blowing pink flowers towards her as she stands on a giant scallop shell. Sandro Botticelli painted the birth of this goddess from sea foam. In 1820, an armless statue of this goddess was found on Milos. For the point, identify this popular subject of art, a Greco-Roman goddess of love.", "answer": "<b> Venus</b> (or<b> Aphrodite</b>; accept<b> Venus with Drawers and Pompoms</b>; accept<b> Venus of Willendorf</b>; accept<b> Birth of Venus</b>; accept<b> Venus de Milo</b> or<b> Aphrodite of Milo(s)</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Innis and Mackintosh theorized that this country\u2019s economic development was driven by the export of \u201cstaples\u201d like fish and wheat. A gold rush in this country spurred the development of Dawson City. This country planned, but did not carry out, a project to detonate nuclear bombs underneath the Athabasca River to boil its oil sands. For the point, name this country, whose economy has been historically bolstered by natural resources, as during the Yukon gold rush.", "answer": "<b> Canada</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Thomas Hankins argued that this movement\u2019s only scientists were Condorcet and d\u2019Alembert, giving them more credit for its successes. This movement was fostered by a vague community of scholars that called themselves the \u201cRepublic of Letters.\u201d Coffeehouses rose to prominence as a place to exchange ideas during this movement. Denis Diderot\u2019s<em> Encyclop\u00b4edie</em> argued for the secularization of education during, for the point, what European intellectual movement that promoted reason and individualism?", "answer": "Age of<b> Enlightenment</b> Page 7", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A company in this industry printed the legendary T206 Honus Wagner baseball card. Starting on January 2, 1971, this industry was banned from advertising on radio and television. In the 1980s, this industry lobbied against labeling laws that announce the presence of carbon monoxide or the potential risk of lung cancer. For the point, name this industry whose ads now feature Surgeon General\u2019s Warnings and that once advertised using mascots like Joe Camel and the Marlboro Man.", "answer": "<b> tobacco</b> industry (accept descriptions of<b> cigarette</b>s,<b> chewing tobacco</b>, and other forms of <b>tobacco</b>; do not accept descriptions of electronic cigarettes) (38) The scherzo of this composer\u2019s fourth symphony features strings playing pizzicato, and he used three Ukrainian folk songs in his second symphony, nicknamed \u201cLittle Russian.\u201d Some scholars think he was forced to commit suicide by a \u201ccourt of honor,\u201d dying nine days after the premiere of his sixth symphony. To commemorate the Battle of Borodino, this composer wrote an overture that quoted \u201cGod Save The Tsar\u201d and \u201cLa Marseillaise\u201d [mar-sigh-yez]. For the point, name this composer of the<em> Pathetique</em> <em>Symphony</em> who included cannon fire in his<em> 1812 Overture</em>. ANSWER: Pyotr Ilyich<b> Tchaikovsky</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The victors of this battle were the first men not to flinch at the dress of the Medes. Arimnestos led an allied contingent of Plataean soldiers to this battle, though the Carneia festival delayed the Spartans from joining it. Miltiades led Athenian forces to victory in this battle, driving back the forces of Darius I. For the point, name this 490 BC victory of Greek forces over Persia, which was legendarily announced to Athens after a 26.2 mile run.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Marathon</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s appearance on<em> Laugh-In</em> was the subject of the first top prize on<em> Who Wants to be A</em> <em>Millionaire?</em>. In<em> Futurama</em>, this man\u2019s head ran for president of Earth. Forrest Gump met this president after participating in ping-pong diplomacy, and in a 2008 movie, this man said \u201cWhen the President does it, that means it\u2019s not illegal.\u201d during an interview with David Frost. For the point, name this president whose fictionalized undoing came after putting Forrest Gump up in the Watergate Hotel.", "answer": "Richard<b> Nixon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This figure was once baited out by the head of a large ox, an event depicted in the Gosforth Cross. One of the few surviving non-Christian runestones, Altuna, recounts how Hymir narrowly escaped death at the hands of this creature after taking a fishing trip too far out into the ocean. Like Fenrir and Hel, this creature was fathered by Angrboda and Loki. It will be slain by Thor at Ragnarok, but not before mortally poisoning Thor with its venom. For the point, identify this lengthy Norse monster that encircles the earthly realm for which it is named.", "answer": "<b> J\u00a8ormungand</b>r (or the<b> Midgard Serpent</b> or the<b> World Serpent</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The power to appoint members to this institution was transferred by the Ovinian Plebiscite. This institution could not meet more than a mile outside of the<em> pomerium</em>. This body\u2019s ultimate decree transferred all power to the executive, ending the ability to announce a dictator. Elected magistrates like aediles and praetors were automatically appointed after their terms to, for the point, what political body, the seat of many patricians in the Roman Republic?", "answer": "<b> Roman Senate</b> (accept<b> Senate</b> after \u201cRoman\u201d is said; prompt on Senate until then)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A city on this body of water was led by Stepan Shahumyan\u2019s 26 Commissars. Operation Barbarossa sought to control a line from this body of water north to Arkhangelsk, the \u201cA-A line.\u201d This body of water was first mapped by Fedor Soimonov during the reign of Peter the Great. The Absheron peninsula on this body of water is an oil hotspot. Astrakhan and Baku are situated on, for the point, what body of water east of the Caucasus mountains, the largest enclosed inland body of water on Earth?", "answer": "<b> Caspian</b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler empowered Llywelyn the Great in Wales by giving him his daughter in marriage. Though he settled his claims to French land in the Treaty of Le Goulet, this ruler lost control of Normandy following the Battle of Bouvines [boo-veen]. Innocent III excommunicated this ruler after he refused to accept Stephen Langton as the Archbishop of Canterbury. In 1215, this brother of Richard I was cornered at Runnymede and forced to concede numerous rights to his barons. For the point, name this English king who signed the Magna Carta.", "answer": "<b> John</b> Lackland (accept<b> John</b> I) Page 9", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Ambiguity over an international boundary near this river\u2019s headwaters led to the proclamation of the unrecognized Indian Stream Republic in 1832. The Windsor Locks were built to allow ships to pass the Enfield Falls on this river, whose mouth was home to the short-lived Saybrook Colony. It passes through the Pioneer Valley in Massachusetts and forms the border between Vermont and New Hampshire. For the point, name this longest New England river, which flows past its namesake state\u2019s capital at Hartford.", "answer": "<b> Connecticut</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One character in this novel crosses out the names of those who live in his realm from the Book of Life and Death. That character from this novel steals peaches of immortality and receives an 8.1 ton staff that can be shrunk down to the size of a needle from the Dragon King of the Eastern Sea. A monk in this novel travels to Vulture Peak with Sandy, Pigsy, and a character who was trapped under a mountain for 500 years. This novel fictionalizes Xuanzang\u2019s journey to obtain Buddhist scriptures from India. For the point, name this Chinese classical novel that features the monkey king, Sun Wukong.", "answer": "<b> Journey to the West</b> (or<b> Xi You Ji</b>; prompt on Monkey)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "During this event, a period of hysteria known as the Irish Night was ended with the return of the king. Henry Sydney, on behalf of the \u201cImmortal Seven,\u201d wrote an invitation letter seeking this event. The Declaration of Indulgence and the repeal of the Test Acts, measures to achieve religious toleration, helped cause this event. In response to this event, Jacobites rebelled numerous times in support of the deposed James II. For the point, name this 1688 event in which William and Mary ascended to the English throne in a remarkably peaceful manner.", "answer": "<b> Glorious Revolution</b> (accept<b> Bloodless Revolution</b>; accept<b> Revolution of 1688</b> until mentioned; prompt on descriptive answers, like \u201cWilliam and Mary taking the throne\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Pope John XXIII [23] tried to mediate this event by asking one side to \u201cnot remain deaf to the cry of humanity.\u201d This event was prompted when the results of Operation Anadyr were photographed by U-2 spy planes. An agreement that Jupiter MRBMs would be removed from Turkey helped end this event, which led to the establishment of a hotline between Moscow and Washington D.C. to mediate further disputes. For the point, name this Cold War scare in which weapons were discovered in Fidel Castro\u2019s country.", "answer": "<b> Cuban Missile</b> Crisis (accept descriptive equivalents; prompt on partial answers) Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This thinker wrote a pamphlet with Gene Weltfish, beginning \u201cThe world is shrinking,\u201d to send to Allied troops during World War II.<em> The Anatomy of Dependence</em> was written as a response to one of this author\u2019s works, which characterized a certain group as both \u201cinsolent and polite.\u201d This author\u2019s definition of culture as \u201cpersonality-writ-large\u201d was included in her<em> Patterns of Culture</em>, and she followed up on that work by contrasting the \u201cshame\u201d and \u201cguilt\u201d cultures of the United States and Japan. For the point, name this Columbia anthropologist, student of Franz Boas, and author of<em> The Chrysanthemum and the</em> <em>Sword</em>.", "answer": "Ruth<b> Benedict</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader was criticized for inviting anti-gay Muslim cleric Shady Alsuleiman to an Iftar dinner. Bob Katter pledged to support this leader if his coalition did not receive a majority of the seats in parliament. This leader rose to power after defeating Tony Abbott in his party\u2019s leadership contest, and was re-elected in July 2016, defeating the Labour Party\u2019s Bill Shorten. For the point, name this current Liberal Prime Minister of Australia.", "answer": "Malcolm<b> Turnbull</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The defeated side of this conflict affirmed a commitment to \u201cno peace, no negotiations, and no recognition\u201d in the Khartoum Resolution. This war began with Operation Focus, a preemptive strike that destroyed much of one side\u2019s air force. Under the leadership of Moshe Dayan, the Golan Heights and Gaza Strip were quickly seized by the winners of this conflict. Gamal Abdel Nasser closure of the Straits of Tiran triggered, for the point, what 1967 war between Israel and an Arab alliance that was over within a week?", "answer": "<b> Six Day</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "According to legend, correspondence written by this man to his opposing general relieved his enemy\u2019s migraine headache. This man wrote \u201cI have determined to avoid the useless sacrifice\u201d in General Order No. 9, a document drafted at the home of Wilmer McLean. After the fall of Petersburg, this leader of the Army of Northern Virginia retreated from Richmond but was surrounded by cavalry a week later near Appomattox Court House. For the point, name this Confederate general who surrendered to Ulysses S. Grant, effectively ending the U.S. Civil War.", "answer": "Robert (Edward)<b> Lee</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A newspaper editor in this state, William Allen White, attacked the Populists in an article wondering\u201cwhat\u2019s the matter with\u201d this state. Quantrill\u2019s Raiders burned a city in this state in 1863, and five settlers were killed by John Brown here in the Pottawatomie massacre. The Lecompton Constitution would have allowed slavery in this state, which was the site of a conflict featuring many \u201cborder ruffians.\u201d For the point, what future Plains state was labeled \u201cbleeding\u201d prior to the Civil War?", "answer": "<b> Kansas</b> Page 12", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this treaty\u2019s negotiations, Sergei Witte threatened to end the ceasefire if the other side refused to drop their reparation claims and accept Sakhalin Island in return. After this treaty was brokered, its mediator earned a Nobel Peace Prize, the first U.S. President to earn one. This treaty ended a war that included two battles of Port Arthur in Manchuria. Teddy Roosevelt helped ensure the signing of, for the point, what 1905 treaty that ended the Russo-Japanese War?", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Portsmouth</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This island was invaded by the Great Heathen Army and Ivar the Boneless after his father Ragnar was executed by a king of Northumbria. The Doom book was a law code compiled on this island. Canute the Great conquered this island, where the Danelaw was dominated by the Norse. Alfred the Great ruled Wessex on, for the point, what island settled by the Anglo-Saxons that is home to the modern countries of Wales, Scotland, and England?", "answer": "Great<b> Britain</b> (do not accept or prompt any other answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A ruler of this country was captured during the Kalabalik of Bender by the Ottoman Empire, where he was hiding in exile. This country faced Augustus the Strong\u2019s coalition of Saxony and Poland-Lithuania, which wanted to claim Livonia from Charles XII. This country\u2019s forces were defeated decisively at Poltava by the newly modernized military of Peter the Great. For the point, name this Scandinavian country that challenged Russia in the Great Northern War.", "answer": "<b> Sweden</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader was accused of election fraud, but only charged with misuse of state resources in the Raj Narain case. This leader\u2019s son, Sanjay, carried out a program of abducting and sterilizing men during the\u201cEmergency.\u201d After launching a raid on the Golden Temple in Amritsar, this leader was assassinated by her Sikh bodyguards. For the point, name this daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru and former Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "<b> I</b>ndira<b> Gandhi</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Thomas Dixon wrote a<em> Historical Romance of</em> this group in which Ben Cameron orders the murder of the rapist Gus. By the 1920s, over one-quarter of the population of Indiana was enrolled in this organization. William Simmons led a 1915 revival of this group at Georgia\u2019s Stone Mountain, where a cross was burned, as inspired by D.W. Griffith\u2019s<em> The Birth of a Nation</em>. Nathan Bedford Forrest was the first Grand Wizard of, for the point, what white supremacist group whose members wear white hoods?", "answer": "<b> Ku Klux Klan</b> (or<b> KKK</b>) Page 15", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}